Guide to the Jerome J. Shestack papers, 1944-2011 and undated, bulk 1965-2000 RL.11610
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jerome J. Shestack papers
1944-2011 and undated
1965-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Shestack, Jerome J.
RL.11610
128 Linear Feet 86 boxes Approximately 57,000 items
Jerome Shestack was a prominent lawyer and human rights advocate. His papers chiefly document the leadership roles he undertook for social justice organizations such as the American Bar Association, the Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, the International League for Human Rights, the United Nations Commission on Human Rights, and many others, and the histories of those entities. Series include extensive correspondence and subject files, organization files, writings and speeches, publications and clippings, as well as a small collection of personal files, photographs, and Shestack's World War II diary. Topics covered in the collection include but are not limited to: the history of the American Bar Association; law and legislation related to international and domestic human and civil rights; American government policies on human rights; Jewish human rights issues; the defense of political dissidents such as Andrei Sakharov; disappeared persons in Argentina; the rights of the mentally disabled; and Shestack's role in standing against the Supreme Court nomination of Robert Bork. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Approximately 57,000 items
Biographical / Historical
Jerome J. Shestack was a prominent Philadelphia lawyer known for his extensive work and leadership as a human rights advocate. He was born in Atlantic City, NJ on February 11, 1923. After serving in the Navy during World War II, Shestack received his law degree from Harvard Law School in 1949. He lived with his family in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania where he joined Schnader, Harrison, Segal and Lewis LLP as a practicing lawyer in 1955. During his time in law, Shestack was involved in a number of professional law organizations, including the American Bar Association, the International Bar Association, and the International Commission of Jurists. He served on the American Bar Association committee on judicial appointments, notably voting against the Supreme Court nomination of Robert Bork in 1987. He was President of the American Bar Association from 1997-1998.
Throughout his professional career, Shestack served as a human rights advocate for marginalized groups in America and around the world. He held leadership roles in several human rights advocacy groups and organizations, including the International League for Human Rights and the Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights. Through these organizations he advocated for the fair treatment of political dissidents and the mentally disabled. He was also an active member of the American Jewish Committee. In 1979, President Jimmy Carter appointed Shestack as the U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations Commission on Human Rights, where he worked to identify and address the human rights needs of member nations. He served as the Ambassador until Ronald Reagan became president in 1980.
In 1991, Shestack joined Wolf Block Schorr and Solis-Cohen LLP as a practicing lawyer, where he worked until returning to Schnader Harrison Segal and Lewis as a retired partner in 2009. Recognized for his groundbreaking work in law and human rights advocacy, Shestack received the American Bar Association Medal in 2006, the highest honor awarded in the organization.
Jerome J. Shestack died in Philadelphia, August 28, 2011.
1923 February 11 Born in Atlantic City, New Jersey to Jewish parents
1943-1946 Served in the US Navy; Wounded on the USS Ticonderoga during World War II
1949 Received Law degree from Harvard Law School
1951 Married Marciarose Schleifer
1955 Joined Schnader Harrison Segal and Lewis LLP in Philadelphia.He served as a practicing lawyer there until 1991.
ca. 1960 Joined the American Bar Association
ca. 1963 Joined the first Board of Trustees for the Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law
ca. 1968 Joined the International League for the Rights of Man (later known as the International League for Human Rights)
ca. 1970 Joined the American Jewish Committee
1976 Became the Chair of the International League for Human Rights
1979 December 10 Appointed as the US Ambassador to the United Nations Commission on Human Rights by President Jimmy Carter
1980s Advocated against mistreatment of political dissidents, notably Andrei Sakharov
1987 Voted against the Supreme Court Nomination of Robert Bork, deeming him "not qualified"
1991 Joined Wolf Block Schorr and Solis-Cohen LLP in Philadelphia as a practicing lawyer.
1997-1998 President of the American Bar Association
2006 Awarded the American Bar Association Medal
2009 Rejoined Schnader Harrison Segal and Lewis LLP as a retired partner
2011 August 18 Died in Philadelphia
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Originals of video and audiotape are closed to use. Patrons must request use copies to access the content of the material.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Jerome J. Shestack papers were received as a gift by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 2014.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Jerome Shestack span the years of 1944 to 2011, and document the leadership roles he undertook for legal and social justice organizations such as the American Bar Association, the Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, the International League for Human Rights, the United Nations Commission on Human Rights, the American Jewish Committee, the International Criminal Court, and many others, and the histories of those entities. Series include extensive correspondence and subject files; organization files; writings by Shestack and others, such as reports, editorials, articles, and speeches; publications and clippings; trial testimonies and proceedings; as well as a small collection of personal files, photographs, and Shestack's World War II diary.
The materials provide insights into Shestack's many professional achievements and how his work in the legal profession intersected his passion for human rights. Shestack held leadership roles in many law and human rights organizations, often simultaneously; therefore, the materials also reveal how organizations often collaborated with one another to address human rights from a legal standpoint. A large portion of the material focuses on Shestack's dedication to the law profession through his active roles in the American Bar Association, which includes his position on the 1987 judicial committee against the Supreme Court nomination of Robert Bork, as well as his role as American Bar Association President from 1997 to 1998.
Other materials in the collection demonstrate Shestack's work to promote and defend human rights on a broad international scale. Significant file groups for countries and their associated human rights cases include Argentina, China, Israel, Russia, and South Africa. His particular interests pertaining to human rights include but are not limited to: law and legislation related to international and domestic human and civil rights; American government policies on human rights; Jewish human rights issues; the defense of political dissidents such as Andrei Sakharov; disappeared persons in Argentina and other human rights abuses; the rights of the mentally disabled; and the history of human rights advocacy.
The worldwide respect Shestack gained for his advocacy work is represented in the collection through extensive correspondence and subject files documenting his connections to notable human rights activists and prominent political leaders, including President Jimmy Carter, President George Bush, René Cassin, and Martin Luther King, Jr.
Some audiovisual materials are scattered throughout the collection: a CNBC interview of Shestack as ABA President, International League for Human Rights Awards Dinner cassettes, Wingspread Interview cassettes, a Court TV Bosnia Trial VHS recording, and a recording of the Independent Counsel Symposium. Original media are closed to use; listening or viewing copies must be made for access.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: American Bar Association; Organizations; Correspondence; Subject Files; Writings and Speeches; and Print Materials.
Civil rights; Civil rights -- Law and legislation; Disappeared persons -- Argentina; Dissenters -- 20th century; Human Rights; Human rights advocacy; Human Rights -- Periodicals; Human rights -- Law and legislation; Human rights workers -- United States -- Correspondence; International law and human rights; Jews -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Jews, American -- Correspondence; Judges -- Selection and appointment -- United States; Justice, Administration of -- United States -- 20th century; Lawyers -- United States -- Correspondence; Mental health laws -- 20th century; People with mental disabilities -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Political persecution -- 20th century; Political rights; Social justice -- United States -- History -- 20th century; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; Argentina -- Politics and government -- 1955-1983; Philadelphia (Pa.); Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1953-1985; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Audiocassettes; Black-and-white photographs; Diaries; Video recordings; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Shestack, Jerome J.; Bork, Robert H.; Sakharov, Andreĭ, 1921-1989; ABA Center for Human Rights; American Bar Association; American Bar Association. Commission on the Mentally Disabled; American Bar Association. Section of Individual Rights and Responsibilities; International League for Human Rights; Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law; United Nations Commission on Human Rights; United States. Supreme Court -- Officials and employees -- Selection and appointment
- American Bar Association, 1960-2009 and undated; Approximately 26 large boxes.
  Scope and Contents
  The American Bar Association series documents Shestack's work as a long-time member of the legal organization. The materials reflect his active participation in multiple American Bar Association (ABA) sections and committees, especially those dedicated to the advancement of human rights and equal opportunity. Highlights of the series include files on the committee that helped negate the Supreme Court nomination of Robert Bork in 1987 as well as files documenting Shestack's work during his time as appointed President of the American Bar Association from 1997 to 1998. The series consists of eight subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Presidential Materials, Sections and Committees, and Internal Reports, ABA Publications and Mailings, Subject Files, and Administrative Files.
  - Correspondence, 1969-2006 and undated
    This subseries consists of correspondence between Shestack and others specifically regarding his work in the American Bar Association. Most of the correspondence was exchanged between Shestack and other members of the American Bar Association, but there is some correspondence between Shestack and members of other organizations or groups working with the ABA for various causes.
    Correspondence topics include support for Shestack in various ABA elections, state bar association activities, and Shestack's acceptance of the ABA Medal. The series begins with correspondence arranged chronologically by Shestack. Other correspondence files are arranged by subject. Related material may be found in the Correspondence series.
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1969-1997 Feb.; 18 folders (Box 1)
      Contains correspondence between Shestack and colleagues regarding his work within the American Bar Association
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1997 Feb-1997 Aug; 16 folders (Box 2)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1997 Sept.-1998 Dec.; 19 folders (Box 3)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1998-2006 and undated; 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Letters of Support for House of Delegates, 1983; 2 folders (Box 4)
      Letters written to Shestack to endorse his candidacy for re-elected Assembly delegate to the House of Delegates of the ABA in 1983.
    - Correspondence by State, 1994 (Box 4)
      Correspondence from colleagues arranged by their state location in the US. Some correspondence refers to Shestack's possible candidacy for ABA President.
    - Correspondence on the Orange County Bar Association, 1999 (Box 4)
    - American Bar Association Medal Correspondence, 2005; 2 folders (Box 4)
      Letters written to the ABA in support of Shestack's nomination for the 2005 ABA Medal
    - American Bar Association Medal Congratulation Letters, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Writings, 1979 December-2001 January and undated
    Files house drafts and final versions of writings and speeches by Shestack on American Bar Association topics and events. Related materials may be found in the Writings and Speeches series and perhaps in the Print Materials series.
    - Writings by Shestack, 1979 Dec.-1997 June; 5 folders (Box 4)
      Speeches, papers, and some articles written by Shestack and directed towards different bar associations and legal groups, and newspapers usually on a broader theme regarding the profession. Some speeches given to honor particular people. Speeches are arranged in chronological groups by month, some speeches given more than once, and they are placed in the appropriate date range. Some speech drafts with marginalia included in this series.
    - Writings by Shestack, 1997 July-2001 Jan. and undated; 7 folders (Box 5)
  - ABA Presidential Materials, 1992-1998 June
    Materials document Shestack's role as American Bar Association President from 1997-1998. Materials span his election campaign, his activities as President-Elect, and his work while in office. Documents include letters of support, articles covering the campaign, Shestack's acceptance speech, presidential reports by Shestack, and an interview of Shestack on CNBC during his presidency, recorded on VHS.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original recording is closed to use; a viewing copy must be made for access. Please contact the Rubenstein Library staff before coming to use this collection.
    - Presidential Campaign Materials, 1992-1996; 8 folders (Box 5)
      Includes letters of endorsement, candidacy announcements for Shestack
    - Presidential Campaign Materials, 1992-1996 (Box 24)
    - Presidential-Elect Materials, 1995-1996; 2 folders (Box 5)
      Includes nomination announcements and news articles about Shestack's election
    - Presidential-Elect Materials, 1995-1996 (Box 24)
    - Presidency Materials, 1997; 6 folders (Box 5)
      Includes articles and correspondence addressing Shestack's work as ABA President.
    - Presidency Materials, 1997 Aug.-1998 June; 12 folders (Box 6)
      Includes ABA Presidency reports and memorandums, conference briefing books, and a 1997 VHS tape of Shestack on CNBC
  - Sections and Committees, 1960-2009 and undated
    This large subseries documents Shestack's work on various ABA sections and committees throughout the entirety of his time as a member of the association.
    Sections and committees of interest are: the Office of Economic Opportunity, the Commission on the Mentally Disabled, and the Section on Individual Rights and Responsibilities, of which Shestack was a founding member. The subseries also contains documents regarding Shestack's work on the ABA Committee of judicial appointments, specifically relating to his vote against Judge Robert Bork's nomination for the Supreme Court. Documents include some correspondence, conference files, reports, and memorandas.
    - American Bar Association Bork Committee, 1987; 12 folders (Box 6)
      Documents regarding the ABA Committee formed to determine whether or not Judge Robert Bork was qualified to fire special prosecutor Archibald Cox as a part of the Watergate Scandal. Includes letters from committee members supporting or denying Bork's qualifications in addition to committee reports and essay commenting on the event.
    - American Bar Association Bork Committee, 1987; 12 folders (Box 7)
    - Central and Eastern European Law Initiative (CEELI), 1996-2008; 6 folders (Box 7)
      Meeting reports, ABA-published Materials, and some correspondence regarding ABA and Shestack's involvement with the Central Eastern European Law Initiative, a nonprofit provider of legal education in the Czech Republic.
    - Central and Eastern European Law Initiative (CEELI), 1996-2008; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Central and Eastern European Law Initiative (CEELI), 1996-2008; 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Federal Judiciary Committee, 1985-1989, 2000-2001; 21 folders (Box 8)
      Reports, member rosters, and some Supreme Court case files concerning or belonging to the Federal Judiciary Committee, a committee that provides peer evaluation of federal judicial nominees.
    - Center for Human Rights, 1973-2009; 26 folders (Box 9)
      Newsletters, reports, and correspondence on various topics of human rights addressed by the Center. Topics include torture, genocide, and human rights work in various countries.
    - Center for Human Rights, 1973-2009; 13 folders (Box 10)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities (IRR) Correspondence, 1965-1991; 10 folders (Box 10)
      Correspondence between Shestack and his colleagues about the activities of the ABA's Section for Individual Rights and Responsibilities. Correspondence from 1991 celebrates the section's anniversary.
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Chicago Trial Cincinnati, 1970; 4 folders (Box 10)
      Correspondence to and from Shestack regarding a controversial Chicago Trial involving the Cincinnati Bar Association and ABA's section on Individual Rights and Responsibilities.
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Chicago Trial Cincinnati, 1970; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Correspondence from the Chicago trial and news clippings
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Constitutional Conventions Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 11)
      Correspondence concerning ABA's involvement in the National Constitution Convention
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities House of Delegates, 1971 (Box 11)
      Oral report by Shestack to the House of Delegates concerning IRR issues and related correspondence
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Campus Dissent Committee, 1969; 3 folders (Box 11)
      Press releases and reports concerning IRR's Committee on Dissent Among College Communities
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities "Birth of A Section", 1991 (Box 11)
      ABA IRR's Human Rights Magazine w/ special feature on IRR Anniversary
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Midyear Meeting Information, 1971 (Box 11)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Genocide Convention, 1970; 3 folders (Box 11)
      Correspondence and reports on the ratification of the IRR-supported Genocide Convention by the United States
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Housing Committee, 1966-1971 (Box 11)
      Correspondence and memorandums regarding IRR's subcommittee on equal opportunity in the housing market
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Freedom from Hunger, 1960s-1970s; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Correspondence and reports from the IRR annual meetings
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Annual Meeting Information, 1969-1971; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Reports from the IRR annual meetings
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Right to Legal Services Committee, 1969-1973; 2 folders (Box 11)
      Correspondence, reports, news clippings, and publications concerning the activities of the Rights to Legal Services Committee, which sought to provide legal services to those who struggled to find such services.
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Right to Legal Services Committee, 1969-1973; 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities-ABA Officers, undated (Box 12)
      News clippings about the ABA-IRR officers.
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Board of Governors, 1970 July 15 (Box 12)
      Board of Governors meeting minutes
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Amnesty, 1970 (Box 12)
      Correspondence between Shestack and colleagues about amnesty and IRR
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Electronic Surveillance, 1971 (Box 12)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Financial Information, 1969-1971; 2 folders (Box 12)
      Reports and charts of IRR funds allocation.
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Law Student Division, 1971 (Box 12)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Ford Foundation, 1969-1974; 4 folders (Box 12)
      Correspondence, reports, and memorandums concerning the IRR's work with the Ford Foundation.
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Committee on Alcoholism, 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 12)
      Correspondence and reports on the IRR committee for alcohol reform
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities American Citizenship Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 12)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities American Indian Committee, 1970 (Box 12)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Committee on Civil Rights and Responsibilities, 1969-1970; 3 folders (Box 12)
      Correspondence and reports on initiatives led by the IRR Civil Rights Committee
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Committee on Committees, 1970 (Box 12)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Committee on Equal Protection of the Law, 1970 (Box 12)
    - IRR Equal Rights for Women Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 13)
    - IRR National Judicial College Files, 1997; 3 folders (Box 13)
      Includes correspondence, reports, and publications by the National Judicial College for the IRR's work with Immigration Law. Also Includes certificates award to Shestack for presentations he conducted as a part of human rights courses conducted through the National Judicial College.
    - IRR Human Rights files, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
      Binder files concerning human rights projects undertaken by the ABA-IRR. Also includes ABA Human Rights publication from July 1971.
    - Committee of International Aspects of Individual Rights and Responsibilities, 1971 (Box 13)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Committees on Rights of the Accused, 1971 (Box 13)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Washington May Day Protest, 1971 May (Box 13)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities State and Local Liaison Committee, 1969 (Box 13)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Committee on Religious Liberty, 1971-1972 (Box 13)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibility Human Rights Publication Materials, 1970-1971 (Box 13)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Overpopulation Committee, 1970; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Assorted Files, 1964-1992; 9 folders (Box 13)
      Assorted correspondence to and from Shestack, memorandums, committee reports, and publications regarding the ABA's Section on Individual Rights and Resposibilities. Original arrangement provided.
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Assorted Files, 1964-1992; 15 folders (Box 14)
    - Individual Rights and Responsibilities Bound Correspondence, 1969 (Box 14)
    - Commission on the Mentally Disabled (CMD) Correspondence, 1975-1977; 4 folders (Box 14)